Louise Nevelson
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Louise Nevelson papers
circa 1903-1979
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Nevelson, Louise
16.8 linear feet
The papers of Louise Nevelson measure approximately 16.8 linear feet and date from circa 1903 to 1979. The collection documents aspects of the life and work of the sculptor, focusing especially on her later career. Papers include correspondence, personal business records, writings, scrapbooks, early art work, photographs, interviews, awards and honorary degrees, books, and an extensive amount of printed material.
Provenance
Louise Nevelson donated her papers in several installments from 1966 to 1979; they were microfilmed upon receipt.
Related Material
Other resources relating to Louise Nevelson in the Archives include oral history interviews with Nevelson conducted by Dorothy Seckler, June 1964-January 14, 1964, and Arnold Glimcher, January 30, 1972. Other material relating to Louise Nevelson, which was collected by her brother Nathan Berliawsky and her son Mike Nevelson, can be found at the Farnsworth Art Museum, Rockland, Maine.
Restrictions on Access
The bulk of this collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of this collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Only the covers and title pages of widely available exhibition catalogs have been scanned. Additional items typically not scanned include photographs of artwork, slides, clippings, publications, and other printed material.
Biographical Note
Louise Nevelson was born in 1899 in Kiev, Russia. Her parents, Isaac and Minna Berliawsky, and their children emigrated to America in 1905 and settled in Rockland, Maine, where the young Louise grew up as a bit of an outsider in local society. She decided upon a career in art at an early age and took some drawing classes in high school, before graduating in 1918. Two years later, she married Charles Nevelson, a wealthy businessman, and moved to New York. She proceeded to study painting, drawing, singing, acting, and eventually dancing. In 1922, Nevelson gave birth to a son, Myron (later called Mike). She eventually separated from her husband in the winter of 1932-1933; and they divorced officially in 1941.
Beginning in 1929, Nevelson began to study art full-time at the Art Students League, where she took classes with Kenneth Hayes Miller and Kimon Nicolaides. In 1931, she went to Europe and studied with Hans Hofmann in Munich before traveling to Italy and France. She returned to New York in 1932 and again studied for a time with Hofmann, who was by now a guest instructor at the Art Students League. In 1933, she met Diego Rivera while he was in New York working on his mural for Rockefeller Center and casually worked as his assistant for a short period. Shortly thereafter, she began to work in sculpture and joined a sculpture class taught by Chaim Gross at the Educational Alliance. She continued to draw and paint, and even took up etching, lithography, and other techniques at different points in her career, but from this time on, she concentrated on sculpture. Her early sculptures were primarily in plaster, clay, and tattistone.
During the thirties, Nevelson exhibited in a number of group shows (both non-juried and competitive ones), garnering some recognition for her work. In 1935, she taught mural painting at the Flatbush Boys Club in Brooklyn, as part of the Works Progress Administration (WPA), then went on to work in the fine-arts division as an easel painter and sculptor until 1939. In 1941, Nevelson had her first solo exhibition at the Nierendorf Gallery, run by Karl Nierendorf who represented her until his death in 1947. Both this and a one-woman show the following year received favorable reviews. It was around this time that she discovered the decorated shoeshine box of Joe Milone, a local tradesman, and arranged to have it exhibited at the Museum of Modern Art, an occasion which received much notice in the press.
In the 1940s, Nevelson produced a great many works in stone, bronze, terra cotta, and wood, most of them being cubist studies of the figure. In 1943, she had a show titled "The Clown as the Center of his World" at the Norlyst Gallery, which featured works on a circus theme constructed from discarded pieces of wood and other material. This new work was not very well received at the time, and it wasn't until the mid-1950s that she began to work with discarded and found objects on a regular basis.
During the early-1950s, Nevelson attempted to exhibit her work as often as possible, eventually receiving various prizes and notices for her work in the press. She continued to struggle financially though and began to teach sculpture classes in the adult education program of the Great Neck, Long Island public schools in order to make ends meet. In 1955, she joined he Grand Central Moderns Gallery, which was run by Colette Roberts, and had several one-woman shows there. These included: "Ancient Games and Ancient Places" in 1955, featuring Bride of the Black Moon, "The Forest" in 1957, featuring First Personage, and "Moon Garden + One" in 1958, featuring her first wall, Sky Cathedral. During this period, she was painting her wood black and putting together entirely black exhibits; she went on to create works in white and gold in the early-1960s. Around this time, she also began to enclose her small sculptures within wooden boxes.
Nevelson joined the Martha Jackson Gallery in 1958, where she received a guaranteed income and finally achieved a certain degree of financial security. Her first show at the gallery, "Sky Columns Presence," took place in the fall of 1959. In 1960, she had her first one-woman exhibition in Europe at the Galerie Daniel Cordier in Paris. Later that year, her work, grouped together as "Dawn's Wedding Feast," was included in the group show, "Sixteen Americans," at the Museum of Modern Art, alongside the work of Jasper Johns, Robert Rauschenburg, and other younger artists. She made her first museum sale in 1962 when the Whitney Museum of American Art purchased the black wall, Young Shadows. That same year, Nevelson's work was selected for the thirty-first Biennale in Venice.
Over the years, Nevelson took on several assistants, including Teddy Haseltine, Tom Kendall, and Diana Mackown, to help in the studio and with daily affairs. She also participated in various artists' groups, and served as President of the New York Chapter of Artists' Equity from 1957 to 1958, and as President of the national organization from 1962 to 1964. She left the Martha Jackson Gallery in 1962, and after a brief, unhappy stint with the Sidney Janis Gallery, she joined the Pace Gallery, which was run by Arnold Glimcher, in the fall of 1963. She proceeded to have shows of new work there about every two years for the remainder of her career. She had her first museum retrospective at the Whitney Museum in 1967, which featured over a hundred of her works from her drawings from the 1930s to her latest constructions. And in 1968, she was elected to the National Institute of Arts and Letters. By this time, Nevelson had achieved both critical and commercial success as an artist.
Nevelson always experimented with new materials; she continued to construct her black wood walls, but also went on make constructions from aluminium, plastic, and metal. In the fall of 1969, she was commissioned by Princeton University to do a monumental outdoor sculpture in Cor-ten steel (her first), and went on to do commissioned works for the Philadelphia Federal Courthouse, and Chase Manhattan Bank in New York, among others. In 1973, the Walker Art Center organized a major exhibition of Nevelson work which traveled around the country over the next two years. In 1975, she designed the chapel for St. Peter's Lutheran Church in midtown Manhattan.
Nevelson was widely honored for her work during her lifetime. Over the years, she received honorary degrees from Rutgers University and Harvard University, among other schools, as well as numerous awards, including the Brandeis University Creative Arts Award in Sculpture and the Skowhegan Medal for Sculpture in 1971, the gold medal for sculpture from the American Academy of Arts and Letters in 1983, and the National Medal of the Arts in 1985. By the time of her death on April 17, 1988, Nevelson was considered by and large one of the most important American sculptors of the twentieth century.
Sources consulted for this biographical note include Louise Nevelson: A Passionate Life by Laurie Lisle and Louise Nevelson by Arnold Glimcher.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Louise Nevelson measure approximately 16.8 linear feet and date from circa 1903 to 1979. The collection documents aspects of the life and work of the sculptor, focusing especially on her later career. Papers include correspondence, personal business records, writings, scrapbooks, early art work, photographs, interviews, awards and honorary degrees, books, and an extensive amount of printed material.
Interviews, awards, and honorary degrees comprise a series of biographical material, along with scattered personal papers such as a graduation program, wedding announcement, teaching certificate, invitations, miscellaneous notes, and material relating to Nevelson's son, Mike. Correspondence consists of letters and enclosures from a wide range of professional contacts, including museums and art centers, universities, art associations, women's and charitable organizations, artists, and philanthropists, among others, concerning the exhibition, sale, and donation of Nevelson's art work, and her various arts-related activities, as well as some letters from friends and family, most extensively from her son, Mike. Correspondence can also be found amongst the subject files, which also include clippings, notes, printed and other material organized according to subject and relating to certain exhibitions, and various artistic and professional activities. Whether this organization originates with Nevelson, one of her assistants, or Archives staff is unknown.
Found amongst Nevelson's business records are consignment receipts, statements, correspondence, inventories, disposition cards, notebooks, and lists, stemming from her business dealings with the Martha Jackson Gallery and related matters, usually carried out by her assistant at the time. Business records relate in particular to the large and complex project of inventorying Nevelson's art work undertaken sometime in the early-1960s. Nevelson's writings consist mostly of poems and poem fragments, as well as a short-lived dream journal and scattered writings on art, and reflect some of her ideas about art in general and her work in particular. Also found are a large number of scrapbooks and an extensive amount of printed material, which likely stem in large part from Nevelson's concern to document and keep a record of her accomplishments. Scrapbooks contain clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, and other material documenting Nevelson's early career from roughly the mid-1930s to the mid-1950s. Also included are loose items comprising a scrapbook of sorts on Mike Nevelson and various scrapbooks compiled by others as mementos of particular events. Printed material includes an extensive amount of clippings and publications, exhibition catalogs and announcements, and a variety of other printed material relating or referring to Nevelson or merely featuring her name in print. Also included are several books, some of which are about or feature segments on Nevelson. This material documents both her critical and commercial success, and her role as personality and minor celebrity in the mass media later in her career, especially during the 1960s and 1970s.
Art work consists of early drawings and watercolors made by Nevelson as a child and adolescent and while studying art in high school and New York, which document her artistic tendencies as youth and her early development as an artist and which provide an interesting contrast to her later work in sculpture. Photographs include ones of the Berliawsky family and Nevelson as a child, adolescent, and young woman in the 1920s and 1930s before she became known as an artist; ones of Nevelson from the mid-1950s to the late-1970s, once she had become known, and began to be honored, as an artist; and ones of Nevelson's art work, as well as of various exibitions and installations of her work. Also included are a number of slides of the artist and her art work, including photographs taken by Dorothy Dehner in the mid-1950s at Louise Nevelson's house on Thirtieth Street.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects-Topical:
Sculpture, Modern -- 20th century -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculpture -- Exhibitions; Women sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York; Sculptors -- New York (State) -- New York -- Interviews
Types of Materials:
Works of art; Interviews; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketches
Arrangement
The Louise Nevelson papers are arranged into nine series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1918-1975 (Boxes 1, 17, OV 21; 0.8 linear feet)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1931-1979 (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
Series 3: Subject Files, 1955-1971, 1977-1978 (Box 3; 0.7 linear feet)
Series 4: Business Records, 1946-1954, 1958-1962 (Boxes 3-5; 1.8 linear feet)
Series 5: Writings, 1936-1970s (Box 5; 0.1 linear feet)
Series 6: Scrapbooks, 1935-1970 (Boxes 5, 18-19, OV 22-27; 1.3 linear feet)
Series 7: Printed Material, 1916, 1930s-1979 (Boxes 6-13, 19, OV 28; 8 linear feet)
Series 8: Art Work, 1905-1929 (Boxes 13, 20; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 9: Photographs, circa 1903-1979 (Boxes 14-15, 20, OV 29; 2.3 linear feet)
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1918-1975, Series 1:; (Boxes 1, 17, OV 21; 0.8 linear feet)
  Series consists of scattered material shedding light on different aspects of Nevelson's life and work. Included are the program of her graduation from Rockland High School, the announcement of her wedding to Charles Nevelson, and a draft of last her will and testament; some papers of her son, Mike Nevelson, such as his high school diploma and certificate of service as a seaman, an autograph book (containing signatures of artists, Louis Eilshemius, Hans Hoffmann, and Kenneth Hayes Miller, among others), a short story, and various exhibition announcements and catalogs; numerous awards and honorary degrees received Nevelson; her teaching certificate, dating from the time she taught in the adult education program of the Great Neck, Long Island public schools; material from various interviews with Nevelson, including transcribed interviews with Louise Elliot Rago and Tal Streeter and an untranscribed interview with Molly Haskell; writings about Nevelson, including a typescript of an article by Robert Rosenblum and a paper by Katherine Rouse; and other miscellaneous papers.
  Biographical material is arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Graduation Program and Wedding Announcement, 1918, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Mike Nevelson Papers (Box 1)
    - Childhood Drawings [?], undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Papers and Official Documents, 1920s, 1940-1944 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Autograph Book, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Writing,undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs,undated, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1921, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1954-1973, (See also Box 17 and OV 21) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Material Pertaining to Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1966-1978, (6 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 1, Folder 9-14)
  - Teaching Certificate, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Financial Records, Check Stubs, 1957-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Interviews with Nevelson, 1958-1975, (3 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Invitations, Programs, and Menus, 1959-1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Writings about Nevelson, 1960-1966 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Biography and Notes, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Draft of Last Will and Testament, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Name Tags, 1970, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Oversize, Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1954-1973, (See Box 1, F8) (Box 17 (sol))
  - Oversize, Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1954-1973, (See Box 1, F8) (Box OV 21)
- Correspondence, 1931-1979, Series 2:; (Boxes 1-2; 1.5 linear feet)
  Series consists primarily of Nevelson's professional correspondence, as well as some personal and family correspondence, including extensive correspondence from her son, Mike. Files are typically made up of letters, invitations, greeting cards, and telegrams received by Nevelson, copies of letters sent on her behalf (by lawyers and assistants) or shared with her by others, and photographs, press releases, clippings, and other printed material enclosed with correspondence. Correspondents include artists, dealers, museums, universities, art critics, collectors, arts-related and social organizations, admirers, along with some friends, colleagues, and family members in addition to her son. (See appendix for a select list of notable correspondents.)
  General correspondence details the exhibition of Nevelson's work in various group and one-man shows; the consignment, sale, and disposition of her work, especially her dealings with the Martha Jackson Gallery and Daniel Cordier (in Europe); her donations of art work to museums and universities, and for auction by charitable organizations; and the various honors and awards received by her later in her career (including the Creative Arts Medal in Sculpture from Brandeis University and honorary degrees from the Philadelphia College of Art and Bowdoin College, among others). General correspondence also concerns Nevelson's various art-related activities, including her participation on various panels, and in workshops, conferences, and lecture series on art; her involvement in professional organizations, such as the Sculptor's Guild; and her service on various award juries and arts committees (such as the Arts and Entertainment Committee for the Rockefeller Team).
  Correspondence from Mike Nevelson includes letters written to his mother as a child, during his time at school and at sea, and during the time he lived and worked in Maine. Letters primarily concern family and personal matters, and document the complicated relationship between mother and son. Some letters also concern art matters, and document their shared interest in sculpture and their mutual support for each other's work over the years.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically, except for letters from Mike Nevelson which are arranged in files at the end of the series.
  - General Correspondence (Box 1)
    - 1931-1933 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - 1941-1949 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - 1950-1953 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - 1961, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - 1962, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 38-40)
    - 1963, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 41-42)
    - 1964, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
    - 1965, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
    - 1966, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 47-48)
    - 1967, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - 1968, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 3-4)
    - 1969 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - 1970, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - 1971, (5 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 7-11)
    - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - 1973, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 13-14)
    - 1974, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 15-16)
    - 1975, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - 1976, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - 1978, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - 1979, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 22-23)
  - Mike Nevelson Letters (Box 2)
    - 1931-1939, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 24-26)
    - 1940 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - 1941 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - 1942 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - 1943 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - 1944 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - 1947-1949 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - 1950-1951 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - 1952 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - 1953 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - 1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - 1955 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - 1956-1957 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - 1958 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - 1959 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 1960 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 1962-1965, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Subject Files, 1955-1971, 1977-1978, Series 3:; (Box 3; 0.7 linear feet)
  Series consists of files of clippings, newsletters, correspondence, notes, announcements, programs, receipts, loan agreements and receipts, and other material, organized according to subject (name of organization or person, place, activity, format). Files relate to Nevelson's activities with various professional and arts-related organizations (such as Artists Equity Association); her participation in various workshops, panels, and conferences (including Meet the Artists course at New York University and the Tamarind Lithography Workshop); the exhibition of her work in other countries, and in museums and galleries, such as The Museum of Modern Art and Wadsworth Atheneum; the handling of certain business matters (including dealings with the gallery owner, Daniel Cordier, restoration of the Nevelson sculpture owned by Nelson Rockefeller that was damaged by fire, and various photograph orders), usually conducted by Nevelson's assistant, Tom Kendall, on her behalf. Files of biographical information and notes also relate to some of Nevelson's activities in publicizing her art work.
  It is not clear whether the subject organization of the files originates with Nevelson (or one her associates) or with Archives staff. The existing organization has for the most part been maintained. Files are arranged alphabetically. Related material can be found amongst the business records and printed material.
  - Amarillo (Texas), 1962, 1964, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - American Abstract Artists, 1959-1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - The Art Gallery (Directories), 1958-1962, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Art Students League, 1955-1960, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Artists Equity Association, 1957-1967, (5 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 5-9)
  - Arts Festival (Williamsport, Pennsylvania), 1968-1970, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Auctions, 1958, 1961, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Bills, Orders, and Receipts, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Biographical Information (Publicity), 1959-1960, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Brooklyn Museum, undated, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - The Club, 1958-1959 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Conference on World Affairs, 1964, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Corber Designs, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Cordier, Daniel, 1960-1962 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Eilshemius, 1960-1961 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Exhibitions, Caracas (Venezuela), 1961 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Exhibitions, Germany, 1961-1962, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 21-22)
  - Exhibitions, Argentina, 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Exhibitions, Los Angeles, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 24)